Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America PE.022
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America
1920-2009
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.022
6 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. The collection consists of agreements, contracts and constitutions, as well as printed material such as fliers, leaflets, newspaper clippings, pamphlets and other publications. The collection offers a general feel for the types of printed matter put out by the Union as well as a brief introduction to and history of the Union and some of it's locals, particularly Local 100, the union for employees of the Metropolitan Transit Authority of New York (MTA).
Historical/Biographical Note
The Transport Workers Union of America came into existence in 1934 as a result of organizing efforts by a core group of workers on New York's Interborough Rapid Transit system, with assistance from Communist Party activists. After slow gains among NYC subway and bus workers and a brief period of affiliation with the International Association of Machinists, the union affiliated with the CIO in 1937 and was granted a broad jurisdiction over all categories of transport workers. Under the dynamic leadership of President Michael J. Quill and a group of organizers who shared his Irish nationalist background and radical outlook, the union soon grew to more than 40,000 members and began organizing nationwide. The largest and most powerful locals of the TWU have been Local 100 (NYC) and Local 234 (Philadelphia), but by the post-World War II period the TWU also had a substantial presence in Chicago, Detroit, San Francisco, Miami, New Orleans, Omaha, and other cities and towns across the nation.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Transport Workers Union, Local 100: Joseph Gayol Files (WAG 85)
Transport Workers Union Local 100: Naomi Allen Files (WAG 295)
Transport Workers Union of America Records (WAG 235)
Transport Workers Union of America: Records of Locals (WAG 234)
Transport Workers Union Oral History Collection (OH 11)
Transport Workers Union of America, Local 100 - Goldstein Interviews Oral History Collection (OH 47)
Transport Workers Union of America Photographs (PHOTOS 32)
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Arrangement
Files are arranged alphabetically. Collection is organized into three series.
Missing Title
I. General Files, 1920-2005
II. Locals, 1937-2009
III. Contracts, 1937-1998
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the Transport Workers Union of America consists of constitutions, circular letters, fliers, pamphlets and articles on the international and locals of the TWU, from 1937 to 2009. Contracts make up half of the collection and include agreements between transportation organizations, airlines and public utilities. Some universities are also represented. Of note are airlines such as Sabena, Eastern and Pan Am, which no longer exist.
The independent transit systems in New York City and the boroughs are represented in all series, with Local 100 comprising a significant portion. Civil rights and the role of women in the union are highlighted in the General Files Series I.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library.
Transport Workers Union of America Flight Attendants brochure was found in repository in May of 2014 and added to this collection. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.071.
The accession number 2014.019 is also associated with this collection.
Akron (Ohio); Philadelphia (Pa.).; New York (N.Y.); Bus drivers |z New York (State) |z New York.; Transport workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York |x History.; Transport workers -- Labor unions -- New York (State); Transport workers |x Labor unions |z United States.; Transport workers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Flight attendants |x Labor unions |z United States.; Labor contract.; Constitutions.; San Francisco (Calif.); Bylaws (administrative records).; Pamphlets.; Fliers (printed matter); Circulars (fliers); Clippings (information artifacts); Articles.; Transport Workers Union of America; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 234 (Philadelphia, Pa.); Interborough Rapid Transit Company; Quill, Mike.; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority; Transport Workers Union of America. Local 100
- Series I: General Files, 1920-2004
  - Constitution, 1937-1948 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1950-1957 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1961-1969 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1973-1989 (Box 1)
  - Constitution, 1993-2001 (Box 1)
  - 40 Hour Week, 1952 (Box 1)
  - Air Transport Division, 1954-1955 (Box 1)
  - American Airlines: Arbitration, 1948 (Box 1)
  - American Labor Party, 1938, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles: Freeman, Joshua, 1980 (Box 1)
  - Articles: Lichtenstein, Alex, 1997-1998 (Box 1)
  - Board of Transportation: Memorandum of Understanding, 1950 (Box 1)
  - Buses: Fifth Avenue Coach Company, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Buses: Queens, 1952-1980, undated (Box 1)
  - Civil Rights, 1934-1986 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 1981 (Box 1)
  - Calendar, 2000 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1980-1989 (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters, 1990-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Civil Service, 1941, 1960 (Box 1)
  - Civil Service Technical Guild-Straphangers Campaign, 1985, undated (Box 1)
  - Constitutional Convention: Report of Proceedings, 1985 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_5a43fc7831a10ae2ac57c07fa06af6d0)
  - Constitutional Convention: Report of the President, 1989 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_920a3bb3a92a61963f6d3800aadf377f)
  - Convention I, 1937-1961 (Box 1)
  - Convention II, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_e7b41fd820493ace4e9254743219490b)
  - Dinner Programs, 1944-1945 (Box 1)
  - Dinner Programs, 1947 (Box 1)
  - Disaffiliation (from AFL-CIO), 2000 (Box 1)
  - Education Department: "Organizing: A Guide for TWU Local Unions", 1996 (Box 1)
  - Faber, Gustav, undated (Box 1)
  - Fifth Avenue Branch Welfare Fund, undated (Box 1)
  - Fliers/ Posters, 1966-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_5932073a92b78ede2390bda5f49152f3)
  - Fliers/ Posters (Scrapbook), 1938 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_6698774771ca2f243b4e15c7c08bd8d6)
  - Freedom of Information Act (FOIA): Requests for Information - FBI Files, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Independent Union of Flight Attendants: Bulletins/ Clippings, 1984-1990 (Box 1, Folder data_value_missing_663e2b98d54dd35b5c75852c8f6b8f2a)
  - Interborough Rapid Transit, 1920-1937 (Box 2)
  - Interborough Rapid Transit (Oversize), 1928, undated (Box MSXOS002, Folder 1)
  - Labor Television Workshop, 1954 (Box 2)
  - Leadership, 1937-2004 (Box 1)
  - Litigation/Mediation, 1942-1961 (Box 2)
  - Membership/ Voters Cards, 1935-1936, 1990, undated (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_ee75fd69061c4efa88aba5020eb2f737)
  - New York City Transit System, 1943-1951 (Box 2)
  - New York City Transit System: Reports, 1941-1943 (Box 2)
  - New York City Transit System: Rules and Regulations, 1952 (Box 2)
  - New York Independent Subway System: Conductors, 1939 (Box 2)
  - New York Rapid Transit Corporation, 1937-1939 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings and Articles, 1947-2009 (Box 2)
  - Newspaper Clippings: Pan Am, 1981-1991 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_ef00c2f8f4d2106cc8012e78d18c0bd0)
  - Pamphlets and Publications I, 1937-1995, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications II, 1937-1995 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications III, 1937-2010 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: The Plane Truth (newsletter), 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_47d43eeb39e48c4ea6be505fd99b6b3f)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: Labor Notes (Newsletter), 1988, 1990 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_919d1580c9f700f2c48c3dde4470b182)
  - Pamphlets and Publications: TWU Express (Newsletter), 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_e4e0d52cc8af0ffe6ae1c2aaf6b0994c)
  - Pan Am/ TWU Correspondence, 1981-1991 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_6f74af898701dab04d0a821eb34764f8)
  - Pan Am/ TWU Agreement, 1988 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_f3b88fa118cf7ff3839535f4f99eab1f)
  - Quill, Michael, 1948-2000 (Box 2)
  - Report: "Economic Report in Support of Transport Workers Union Contract Reform", 1965 (Box 2)
  - Society of Afro-American Transit Employees, 1969 (Box 2)
  - Strike, 1985 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_572dcf9af4109b2872e0a4981a6b7982)
  - Strike/ Pension, 1983-1987 (Box 2, Folder data_value_missing_c2ad7acbeab5cecbc28b75165dab1fe1)
  - Transportation Brotherhoods' Publicity Bureau, undated (Box 2)
  - Unification, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Wages/Collective Bargaining, 1937, 1979 (Box 2)
  - Women, 1950-1988 (Box 2)
- Series II: Locals, 1938-2009
  - Local 1 (Akron, OH), 1960, undated (Box 2)
  - Local 16, undated (Box 2)
  - Local 100 (New York City), 1948-2005, 2010 (Box 2)
  - Local 100: Agreement with Manhattan and Bronx Surface Transportation Authority, 1971-1991 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: All Union Campaign Committee, 1942 (Box 2)
  - Local 100: By-Laws, 1950-1987 (Box 2)
  - Local 100: Campaign to Stop Corporate Welfare and Support Public Transit, circa 2000
  - Local 100: Cards, 1939-1944, undated (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_fc82caaf7085da3a1c5f3393b8494c9a)
  - Local 100: Circular Letters, 1939-2006 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Hell on Wheels: Newsletter, 1989 (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_75f379d7411efa94307f2963815d9106)
  - Local 100: History I, 1938-2009 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: History II, 1938-2009 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: History 10th Anniversary, 1944 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Members First, 2000-2003, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 100: New Directions, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Rank and File - The Advocate, 2001 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Rank and File Committee for TWU Democracy-Transit News, 1949 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Save the Fare, circa 2002 (Box 3)
  - Local 100: Strike 1980, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 101, 1942-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 206 (New Orleans), 1995 (Box 3)
  - Local 225, 1962-1966 (Box 3)
  - Local 228 (Omaha, NE), undated (Box 3)
  - Local 234 (Philadelphia, PA): Articles; Clippings, 1962-1998 (Box 3)
  - Local 234 (Philadelphia, PA): Publications about, 1944-1960 (Box 3)
  - Local 241, 1955-2002 (Box 3)
  - Local 250 (San Francisco, CA), 1992 (Box 3)
  - Local 252 (Nassau, Suffolk), 1947-1950 (Box 3)
  - Local 300: City-Wide Taxi Workers, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 501, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
  - Local 504 (Air Transport, NY), 1986, undated (Box 3)
    - unspecified
  - Local 504: Articles/ Correspondence, 1990 (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_a57284fd1713b44ab2b1e7ba79c01565)
  - Local 504: Convention, 1989 (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_441ea82fd6d33e179b3682772a1b28ff)
  - Local 504: Elections, 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_706ed79b668d83efd2d2284f06389623)
  - Local 504: Elections: Cartoons, 1989, undated (Box 3, Folder data_value_missing_b982794a4f698d337d09cccb2459d215)
  - Local 505 (San Bruno, CA), 1962-1968 (Box 3)
  - Local 550 (Airline Stewards and Stewardesses), 1963-1967 (Box 3)
  - Local 550 (Airline Stewards and Stewardesses), 1961-1971, undated (Box 3)
  - Local 553, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Local 1179 (Green Bus Lines, Jamaica, NY), 1948 (Box 3)
  - Local 1400, 1990s (Box 3)
  - Local 1463, 1960 (Box 3)
    - Local 2071, undated (Box 3)
  - Locals: By-Laws, various, 1946-1952, undated (Box 3)
  - Locals: By-Laws, various, 1945-1974 (Box 3)
  - Locals: Lists of, 1952, undated (Box 3)
- Series III: Contracts, 1937-1998 (Box 5, Box 6, Box 4)
  - Contracts, 1937-1998 (Box 4-6)